Guide to the Consumer Reports. Helen Canoyer papers, 1938-1968 and undated RL.11809
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Helen Canoyer papers
1938-1968 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11809
3.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Helen Gertrude Canoyer was an author, home economist and educator who served as Dean of the Home Economics colleges at Cornell University and the University of Massachusetts. The Helen Canoyer papers include correspondence, clippings, news releases, lecture notes, texts to speeches and articles and other printed materials. An audio tape contains an interview of Canoyer. Much of the materials pertain to Canoyer's work with the Consumer Advisory Council, its administration and its efforts to advocate for consumer protection, consumer education and home economics. Other materials pertain to conferences, personal and professional correspondence, and writings. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Consumer Advisory Council files; Personal and Professional files; Audiovisual materials
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Helen Gertrude Canoyer was an author, home economist and educator who served as Dean of the Home Economics colleges at Cornell University and the University of Massachusetts.
Helen Canoyer was born in Minnesota in 1903. She attended the University of Minnesota (BS, MS, PhD in 1940, the first woman to graduate with a doctorate at the university) and taught economics and marketing there until World War II. During the war Canoyer served with the War Production Board, Department of Commerce and with the Office of Alien Property Custodian. She became Dean of the College of Home Economics at Cornell University in 1954 and held the position until she retired in 1968; she was the first woman faculty member in the Graduate School of Business and Public Administration at Cornell. In 1962 President Kennedy appointed Canoyer to lead the Consumer Advisory Council. In 1971 Canoyer was named Dean of the College of Home Economics at the University of Massachusetts. Canoyer died in San Francisco in 1984.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Helen Canoyer papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports. Frances Warne papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Information Center vertical file
J. Walter Thompson Company. Public relations records
McCann-Erickson vertical file
Collection Overview
The Helen Canoyer papers include correspondence, clippings, news releases, lecture notes, texts to speeches and articles and other printed materials. An audio tape contains an interview of Canoyer. Much of the materials pertain to Canoyer's work with the Consumer Advisory Council, its administration and its efforts to advocate for consumer protection, consumer education and home economics. Other materials pertain to conferences, personal and professional correspondence, and writings.
consumer protection; Consumer education; Home economics -- United States -- History; Canoyer, Helen Gertrude, 1903-1984; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; United States. Consumer Advisory Council
- Consumer Advisory Council, 1962-1966 and undated; 1
  - General Files, 1962-1966 and undated; 1
    - Appontment of Esther Peterson and establishment of the Consumer Advisory Council, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Budget, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Clippings--Canoyer appointment, etc., 1964 (Box 1)
    - Committee no. 1--Consumer standards, grades, labels, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Committee no. 2--Consumer-government communication, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Committee no. 3--Consumer representation, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Committee no. 4--Consumer credit and economic welfare, 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Committee no. 5--Interrelation, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Committees, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Consumer Conference, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Executive Order establishing the President's Committee on Consumer Interests and the Consumer Advisory Council, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Expense vouchers, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Initial materials--Council founding, etc., 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Joint resolution on tire safety, 1964 (Box 1)
    - List of suggested topics for the Council, undated (Box 1)
    - Lists of representatives, members, etc., 1962-1964 (Box 1)
    - Lists of representatives, members, etc., 1964 (Box 6)
    - Massachusetts Consumer Act, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes and correspondence, 1962 July-Sept.; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes and correspondence, 1962 Nov.-1964; 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Memoranda and correspondence, 1962-1965; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Memoranda and correspondence, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Messages from the President, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - News releases, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - News releases, 1964-1965 (Box 6)
    - Newsletter proposal, 1963 (Box 2)
    - President's Committee on Consumer Interests, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - President's Committee on Consumer Interests--Group photograph, undated (Box 2)
    - Recommendations, 1963; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Resolutions, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Resolutions, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Staff report, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Status report on legislation, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
    - Summary statement on the Council, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Terms of reference, undated (Box 3)
    - Walter Heller (Council of Economic Advisors), 1962-1963 (Box 3)
  - Speeches, reports, etc., 1962-1966 and undated; 2
    - Advice to Esther Peterson (Helen Nelson), 1964 (Box 3)
    - Consumer Advisory Council speech by Canoyer, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Consumer Problems and Consumer Education Needs (Margaret Brown, USDA), 1963 (Box 3)
    - Further Thoughts on the Proposed Consumer Committee (Caroline Ware), 1963 (Box 3)
    - Government Consumer Programs in Europe (David Swankin, John Walsh), 1966 (Box 3)
    - Jacob Javits report on the Senate, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Note cards, undated (Box 3)
    - Statement to President Kennedy (Canoyer), 1963 (Box 3)
    - The Consumer Advisory Council: Innovation in Consumer Representation (Robert Lampman), 1963 (Box 3)
    - The New Frontier and the Consumer Interest (Robert Lampman), 1963 (Box 3)
- Personal and Professional Files, 1938-1968 and undated; 2
  - Academic Files, 1950-1953 and undated; 3
    - Class record book, University of Minnesota, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Consumer Credit course notes, undated (Box 3)
    - Consumer Movement course notes, undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Economics of Consumption, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Marketing Theory seminar, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Marketing Theory seminar, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Seminar in Marketing, undated (Box 4)
  - General Files, 1940-1968; 4
    - Chronological files, 1955-1968; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Consumer Conference, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Consumer Education Conference, 1940 (Box 4)
    - Economic Conference, 1955, 1960; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - NASULGC (National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges) Home Economics Conference, 1968 (Box 4)
    - New Mexico State University (job offer), 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - New York State Women's Council, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Speeches, Reports, etc., 1938-1968; 5
    - Consumer Advisory Council: Its Role in Consumer Representation, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Consumer Advisory Council meeting opening statements, 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - Effectiveness as Consumers, 1954 (Box 5)
    - For the Consumer, What Breakthroughs?, 1966 (Box 5)
    - Government and the Consumer, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Government and the Consumer: Representation and Education, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Is the Consumer King or Slave?, 1954 (Box 5)
    - Middlemen in the Domestic Textile Trade of Great Britain 1800-1860, 1938 (Box 5)
    - New Horizons in Extending Home Economics, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Preparation in Economics as an Essential for Extension Personnel, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Retail Chain Stores in Great Britain from 1900-1930, 1930s (Box 5)
    - Some Observations Concerning Economics of Consumption, 1952 (Box 5)
    - The Changing Mission of Home Economics, 1968 (Box 5)
    - The Consumer Advisory Council: Its Origin, Purpose and Problems, 1963 (Box 5)
    - The Consumer in the American Economy, 1964 (Box 5)
    - The Functioning and Significance of the Consumer in the American Economy, 1954 (Box 5)
    - The Role of the Consumer in Our Economy: Theory and Reality, 1963 (Box 5)
    - The Role of the Consumer in Our Society, 1964 (Box 5)
    - The Role of the Home Economist in Consumer Education, 1958 (Box 5)
    - The Value of Economics to Home Economics, 1955 (Box 5)
    - The Work of the Consumer Advisory Council, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Welcome remarks--Conference for Home Economists Working with Low-Income Families, 1965 (Box 5)
    - What's Being Done to Make the American Homemaker a Better Consumer, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Speeches, Reports, etc.--By Others, 1968; 6
    - A Department Head Examines the Specialist-Generalist Question (S.J. Ritchey, Va. Tech.), 1968 (Box 5)
    - Organization in Higher Education (Paul Dressel, Michigan State), 1968 (Box 5)
    - Research and Graduate Study (Margaret Hard), 1968 (Box 5)
    - The Case for Specialization and Generalization (Jane Rees), 1968 (Box 5)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1959; 3
  - Interview with Helen Canoyer by Marth Brooks, WGY, "Sumptuary Savvy" TRT 13:35, 1959 (Box 5, Audio-reel RL11809-RR-001)